你好,学生
hello students
欢迎来到PWN学院的下一个视频
welcome to the next video in the pwn college
shellcoding模块
shellcoding module
今天我们要讲的是
today we're going to be talking about
在shell编码中可能面临的常见挑战
common challenges that you might face in shellcoding
我希望你已经看过本模块之前的视频
I hope you've seen the previous videos in this module
否则，可能无法理解
otherwise this might not make sense
我们开始吧
let's get rolling
我们先讲一个
all right we're gonna start with something
你不一定会遇到
that is not necessarily a challenge that you'll run into
但是遇到时会被它困扰的问题
but more of a hurdle that a lot of people encounter
访问内存的大小
we're going to talk about sizes of memory accesses
如果你还记得汇编基础那节课的话
if you recall from the assembly fundamentals lecture
你可以访问不同大小的寄存器
you can access registers in different sizes
这些不同的大小在内存访问中也有类似的情况
well those different sizes have an analog in memory access as well
你也可以访问不同大小的内存
you can access memory in different sizes as well
所以
so
比如将寄存器中数据加载到内存
in the kind of simple case where you are moving a register into a memory location
这一举动
this move
例如，第一个单字节的例子
for example this 1st single byte example will
会加载RBX的最低有效字节
move the least significant byte of RBX
进入RAX所指向的内存位置
into the memory location pointed to by RAX
这些写入的大小是根据寄存器的大小来确定的
these writes are sized according to the size of the the register
这很简单
right so that's nice and simple
如果你写BL，它会写一个字节。BX 2字节
if you write BL it will write a single byte.  BX 2 bytes
EBX 4字节RBX 8字节
EBX 4 bytes RBX 8 bytes
很简单
nice and simple
没什么特别疯狂的
nothing super crazy there
有时候，当你写一些立即数的时候，比如常数
sometimes though when you're writing for example just immediate values constants
事情可能会变得有点棘手
things might get a little trickier
假设你写入数字5
let's say you're writing number 5
会写入多少字节？
how many bytes is that
你可以用一字节存储5
technically speaking you can fit the number 5 into 1B
但也许你想存储的是0....05
but maybe you mean 0....05
这你就需要8个字节
and you want 8 bytes or something
在这些情况下，你可以显式地指定写入的大小以避免任何歧义
right in these cases you can explicitly specify the size of the write to avoid any ambiguity
当然你也可以用上面的方式来指定大小
you can also specify it in the original case as well
只是记住，存在下面例子中的情况
just keep in mind there are cases such as this in the bottom case
你必须显示指定大小
you have to specify on this
如果你不指定，汇编程序就会向你报一些难以理解的错误
and the assembler if you don't specify it will complain to you with kind of a hard to understand errors
现在你知道了如何向内存写入特定大小的数据
now you know how to write memory with certain sizes
好了，让我们开始真正的挑战吧
all right let's move on to actual challenges
谈论在特定情况下该怎么做，比如
talk about what to do in situations
你可以注入shellcode，但有些值不能出现在你的shellcode中
where you can inject shellcode but  there are certain values that cannot be present in your shellcode
这其实是一种很常见的情况
this is actually a very common situation
我们将在以后的模块中经常讨论
often as we'll discuss later in future modules
strcpy是个问题
strcpy is kind of a problem child
经常导致缓冲区溢出的函数
sort of function that leads to buffer overflows frequently
如果你用strcpy注入shellcode
if you're injecting your shellcode with strcpy
那么你的shellcode不能包含空字节
then your shellcode cannot contain null bytes
因为当strcpy遇到空字节时，它将终止并停止复制
because strcpy will terminate and stop copying when it hits a null byte
因为那是字符串结束的标志
because that's when strings end
这是一个常见问题，还有其他常见问题
so that's one common problem and other common problems
\n新行符，比如scanf gets getline fgets
new lines if you're talking about something like scanf gets getline fgets
这些也是非常常见的不安全功能
these are also very common unsafe functions
这会导致溢出等等
that lead to overwrites and so forth and
它们遇到\n就停止
they terminate on a new line
实际上scanf遇到\r、空格、制表符也会结束
and actually scanf also terminates on a character return space tab what have you write
还有一些特殊字符，比如0x7f
then there are other kind of special characters like 0x7f
在某些协议中代表一些特殊的东西
in certain protocols is mean something special
在其它协议中就是普通字符
and other ones these are just kind of common ones
所以你必须准备好编写不包含这些字符的shellcode
so you have to be ready to write shellcode that optimally doesn't include these characters
否则你的shellcode在传输过程中
because otherwise your shellcode will get messed up in  transfer basically
或者在写入的过程中变得一团糟
or in one of the write processes or something
如何确保你的shellcode不包含这些坏字符
so how do you make sure that your shellcode doesn't contain these bad characters
在汇编中有很多种表达同一件事的方法
there's a lot of ways to express the same thing in assembly
就像在C中一样
just like there is in C
就像在python中一样
just like there is in python
有很多方法可以做你想做的事情
there are many ways to do some specific thing you're trying to do
这里有几个由坏到好的例子，都达到了同样的效果
here a couple of kind of bad to good examples that achieve the same thing
首先，说说 mov RAX, 0
at the top here we do move RAX comma zero
这里你想把0写到RAX中
here you want to write 0 into RAX
这里面有大量的空字节
this has a ton of null bytes in it
为什么? 因为mov rax 0
why because move rax 0
它将一个64位的值移动到rax中
it moves a 64 bit value into rax
64位的值是0，但是有8个字节的0
that's 64 bit value is  0 but 8 bytes of zeros
在这种情况下，我们可以用xor rax rax来代替它
instead we can replace it in this case with something like xor rax rax
它清空了RAX也把它设为0，而且机器码更短
which just clears out RAX also sets it to 0 and is much shorter right
实际上还有机器码更简短的形式
there are actually even shorter forms of that call
你可以执行xor eax eax
you can do xor EAX EAX
如果你还记得汇编基础那节课的话
which if you remember the assembly fundamental lecture
它也将RAX中最重要的字节归零
also zeros out the most significant bytes of RAX as well
但这只是一个例子
but that's one example right
假设你想要加载一些值到RAX
let's say you wanted to actually move some value to RAX
你可以，执行 mov rax 5
you can you still can right if you do move rax 5
但你也会遇到和之前空字节同样的问题
you have the same problem with just one of those null bytes
现在8字节其中之一是5，不是null
one of those you know many bytes of nulls is now a 5 instead of a null
但其余的仍然是空字节
and but the rest are still null bytes
所以还是存在这个问题
so you still have this problem
当然，你可以清零rax，然后加载5到al寄存器
well you can of course 0 out rax and then move 5 into just al right
也很简单
nice and simple there as well
你加载5到al
you move 5 into al
那么rax只有0000…0005
so the then rax has just 0000...0005
非常简单的
very simple
好吧
all right
假设你想换一种方式
let's say you want to move another way to do things
如果你试图避免使用的不是零而是\n
if you are trying to avoid not zeros but a new line for example
你想把10加载到rax
and you want to move 10 into rax
10的十六进制是0x0a
10 also known as in hexa decimal as 0x0a
是换行符的ASCII码值
is the new line character in ASCII
这是个大问题
so this is a big problem
如果你找到的是scanf或者其他类似的方式注入shellcode
if you have a scanf or some other analogous way of injecting a shellcode
它遇到\n将终止读取
it will terminate the read on that new line
但没关系，你也可以
but that's okay you can instead
加载9到rax，然后增加rax或
move 9 into it and then increment rax or
你可以用xor清零rax，然后inc 10次
you can xor it xor rax rax and then do inc 10 times
或者使用其它方法
or it's not anything along those lines
有很多不同的方法可以做到这一点
there are a lot of different ways to do this
做到避免在你的shellcode中有10
that avoids having a literal 10 in your shellcode
也就是\n
literal new line
好了，最后一个，第四件事
all right final one the 4th thing here
如果我们想将flag值或/flag这部分字符串加载到RBX
if we want to move the flag value into rbx or slash flag the partial string
并且这里有空字节
and there it has null bytes in it
你知道的
and this is you know
这时再用xor清零rax然后用
it would not be reasonable to xor rax rax and then have
大量的inc rax 来编写shellcode是不合理的
you know gigabytes and gigabytes of inc rax shellcode
显然我们可以换一种方法
obviously we can do something different
我们可以把flag这个词反序
we can move just the word flag backwards
因为这是小端序
this is little endian yeah
放到ebx中，然后左移ebx8位
into ebx then we shift ebx to the left by 8 bits
然后我们向刚刚左移空出来的最低有效字节放入斜杠
and then we move in to the least significant byte that just cleared up the forward slash
最后我们得到了这个galf/
and then we end up with backwards this forward slash flag
然后当我们把它写到内存或者做其他事情的时候
right then when we wirte it to memory or whatever we do
我们有了/flag
we'll have slash flag right
所以我们构建了需要的值
so we build the value
我们可以用很多不同的方式来构建
we can build in in many different ways
我们可以用不同的指令
and we can use different instructions
即使指令本身给我们带来了问题
even if the instruction itself is causing a problem for us
例如，如果你不能用xor
for example if you can't use xor
你可以使用其他的指令来做类似的事情
there are other instructions that you can use that do similar things right
有一些工具可以自动帮你完成这些
there are tools that will do this automatically for you
我推荐
I would recommend
特别是当你学习shellcode的时候
especially as you learn shellcode
尤其是在这个作业中
and especially in this homework
不要使用它们
don't use them
它们并不总是有效
they don't always work
而且
and
当它们不起作用的时候
when they don't work
不清楚是你的shellcode不正确
it's not clear if it's your shellcode that's incorrect
还是这些工具正在尝试的
or these tools that are trying to
约束绕过方法不正确的
make your shellcode pass certain constraints are incorrect
你最终会花费大量的时间进行调试
you end up spending insane amounts of time debugging
我不推荐使用它们
I wouldn't recommend it
只需编写你的shellcode，并找出如何绕过
just write your shellcode and figure out how to bypass
不管有什么限制条件
whatever constraints that you have
不管有哪些字节不能用等等
whatever bytes you can't use and so forth
用手
by hand
好的，继续
all right rolling on
你可能会遇到这样的情况
you might run into a situation where
某些指令是完全禁止的
certain instructions are simply forbidden
或者有约束条件
or where there are constraints
很难保留shellcode的功能性并绕过约束
where it's very hard to get around them and still have functional shellcode
好吧
well
在冯·诺依曼架构中
remember in a Von Neumann architecture
代码和数据是一回事
code and data are the same thing
通常在你写shellcode的时候
and oftentimes by the time you're wroting shellcode
你有一个区域，你可以写入，然后执行
you have a region that you were able to write to and then are able to execute
这样你就有了可写入的代码
so you have writable code
这很重要
this is important
你可以做一些非常聪明的事情
you can do very clever stuff
假设
so let's say
出于某种原因，我禁止在shellcode中使用int 3的调试操作码
for whatever reason I forbade int 3 the debug op code in shellcode or whatever
漏洞程序不会接受它
the vulnerable program wouldn't accept that
或者应用了类似的约束条件可以阻止int 3
or there was a constraint applied somewhere along the line that would negated
但你需要使用int 3
and you really need to use int 3
int 3在二进制是cc字节十六进制的0x cc
int 3 in assembly in binary is cc the byte 0x cc in Hexadecimal
所以你能做的就是写一个字节CB然后加1
so what you can do is write a byte CB and increment it
这正是这段代码所做的
and that's exactly what this little snippet does
它将rip指向的指令增加1
it increments the instruction point into by the instruction pointer
也就是将要执行的下一条指令
which is going to be the next instruction to execute
加一，然后执行
increments it and then it'll execute
你必须确保在测试的时候
you'll have to make sure when testing this that
你使用的是我们在本模块前面讨论过的shellcode运行和测试方法
you're using the shellcode running and testing method that we talked about earlier in this module
你必须确保你编译的shellcode
you have to make sure that you compile your shellcode
.text段是可写的
with the .text segment being writable
这是非常重要的
that's important
默认是不可写，只可读的
otherwise by default it is not it's readable
那将很令人头疼
and then it's it's a pain in the bottom
你可以这样做
so you can do this right here
-Wl,-N
this dash capital w low case L comma dash n
Wl告诉GCC将这个选项传递给链接器
capital WL tells GCC to pass this option to the linker
这个选项可以做很多事情
and this option does a number of things
一个副作用是使text段可写
that as a side effect makes a wirteable text segment
然后你就可以在执行的时候做这些事情
and then you can do this sort of thing of course at execution time
通常
usually
通常你的shellcode需要是可写的，但并不总是如此
frequently your shellcode is wirteable but not always
好吧
all right
你还能做什么呢
what else can you do
如果你的shellcode中的约束很难绕过
well if constraints in your shellcode are so hard
一个系统调用都用不了
that you just can't get a system call out
你无法实现想让shellcode实现的任何目标
that you can't achieve whatever goal you want your shellcode to achieve
你总是可以加载更多的shellcode
you can always load more shellcode
你一般可以加载更多的shellcode
not always but frequently you can load more shellcode
这叫做多级shellcode
right this called a multi stage shellcode
由阶段一加载阶段二
you have stage one that reads in stage 2
假设你有阶段一
so let's say that you had stage one
你只能勉强实现阶段1的shellcode
and you could just barely create a stage one shellcode
它可以从标准输入读取到指令指针指向的缓冲区
that could call read from standered input into the buffer point to by the instruction pointer
也就是下一条要执行的指令
which will be the next instruction to execute
读入1000字节，如果你能做到
of 1000 bytes if you manage to execute that
并且你的shellcode是可写的
and your shellcode is wirteable
那么你就可以
then you can
直接在指令指针前面读入更多的shellcode
you would read in more shellcode directly in front of the instruction pointer
让它执行
and have it execute right
这是绕过复杂过滤器的好方法
that's a pretty good way of bypassing complex filters
在这个作业中，你们可能需要这样做
and in this assignment you will likely have to do that
提示一下
just as a quick note for
这很难做到，在不同的架构上更难做到
this sort of thing is kind of hard to do harder to do on different architectures
在x86 32位架构上，这令人头疼
on x86 32 bit it's a pain in the butt
我的意思是，这是可行的，但它有它的警告
I mean it's doable but it has its caveat
在AMD 64上，这其实非常简单
on AMD 64 this is actually super easy
例如，您可以将rip指向的内存有效地址加载到rax中
you can load effective address of the memory pointed to by the instruction pointer into rax for example
超级简单
super easy
我猜在这种情况下，我们想要加载到RSI中
I guess in this case we'd wanted to be loaded into our RSI
好吧
all right
很好，这就是你绕过
cool um so that is um how you would bypass
非常强的过滤器
let's say a really hard filter
能使实现有用shellcode变得很难的过滤器
that makes it very difficult to do reasonable things
所以你可以试着写更小的shellcode来读取更大的真实shellcode
so instead you can try to just write smaller shellcode that reads in your bigger real shellcode
好吧
all right
最后讲一下shellcode管理
finally just a note on shellcode mangling
你的shellcode可能会乱糟糟的，无法识别
your shellcode might be pretty messed up and unrecognizable
有的挑战题目可能会整理你的shellcode
a challenge might sort your shellcode
一般来说，这可能只会出现在shellcode挑战题目中
this is something that generally speaking will likely only happen in shellcoding challenges
但我见过有shellcode必须以特定的方式编写
but I've seen shellcode that had to be written in a way that
比如，首先你提供的数据是未压缩的
the data you provided is 1st uncompressed
然后它会导致shellcode执行
and then that results in shellcode execution right
shellcode被压缩后就无效了（估计漏洞程序会先压缩用户输入）
so the shellcode has to not really survive compression
但未压缩的数据必须是你的shellcode
but your data when uncompressed has to be your shellcode
可能会用密钥加解密输入的shellcode
I might be encrypted or decrypted with some key
可能会遇到很多不同的情况
a lot of different things that could happen
我的建议是逆推
my advice to you is to start backwards
先想想shellcode运行时的样子
think about what do I want my shellcode to look like when it executes
然后想想
and then think okay
要达到那个样子需要向程序提供什么
now what do I have to provide to the program to make that happen
一步一步来
just step by step right
如果程序先解压缩你的shellcode
if the program uncompresses your shellcode
你想要shellcode在解压缩后执行
and you want your shellcode to execute after being uncompressed
那么写完shellcode后先压缩一下再注入
you start with your shellcode and you compress it
好的
right
这很简单
that's fairly straightforward
但这个小概念，有时很难理顺
but it's a small concept that is sometimes stricky to wrap your head around
好吧
alright
我要提的最后一点
final thing I'll mention
有时候你的shellcode不能直接与你交互
there are times when your shellcode cannot directly talk to you
5个文件描述符全部关闭或
all the 5 descriptors are closed or
你的shellcode实际上运行在某个电厂的嵌入式设备上
your shellcode is actually running on some embedded device in a power plant somewhere
因为你发起了一些不应该做的疯狂攻击，
because you're launching some crazy attack that you shouldn't be
除此之外你还能如何传递flag呢？
how else can you communicate the flag right
如果shellcode和你没有直接的连接
if you don't have a direct connection back to yourself
还是有很多不同的方法能通信
there are a lot of different ways
当然，它们是非常依赖情境的
they are very situational dependent of course
但是总的思想是
but the general idea is
只要你能传递一位信息
if you can communicate one bit of information
那就一位一位地传
then you can communicate just one bit
可能用程序挂起或者不挂起来表示1位信息
and that one bit could be the program hung or didn't hang
或者是 程序崩溃或没有崩溃
the program crashed or didn't crash
又或者是其他可以从shellcode传递给观察者的东西
or any other large amount of things  that you could convey from your shellcode back to you the observer
在非常偏远的情况下，它可以是DNS查找之类的东西
in very remote scenarios it can be stuff like DNS lookups
它可以是很多不同的东西
it can be a lot of different things
但这超出了本模块的范围
but that's out of the scope of this module
但是你需要理解这个概念
but you will need to understand this concept
来通过我们发起的所有挑战
to pass all of the challenges that we're launching
好
alright
接下来讲讲shellcode编写和调试的有用工具
useful tools for shellcode writing and debugging
我已经在汇编基础中提到了rappel
I mentioned rappel already in the assembly fundamentals
我发了一个有AMD 64操作码列表的链接
and I sent a link or had a link to the AMD 64 opcode listing
对于查看在特定约束下可以使用哪些指令很有用
that's very useful see what instructions you can use given certain constrains
再加一些其他的
add a couple other ones
Pwntools是一个非常好的库
pwntools is a very nice library
不仅仅是用来编写shellcode
not just for writing the exploitation shellcode
而且还用于启动漏洞程序并与之交互
but also for launching and interacting with the vulnerable program
这是非常好的，我强烈推荐使用它
it's very good for that I highly recommend using it
Pwntools有内置shellcode
pwntools has shellcode that it can generate for you
我建议这次作业不要用这个
I would recommend not using that for this assignment
它只适用于前几关
it'll work for the 1st couple of levels
但这在学习阶段不能帮助你
but it's going to do you a big disservice afterwards
当遇到它无法解决的挑战，你也无法解决
when you kind of hit a wall on levels that can no longer solve
最后对于调试你的shellcode
finally for debugging your source your shellcode
显然，你将学会爱上GDB
obviously you will learn to love GDB
如果你对GDB进行一点修改，那么它会更容易
GDB is a little easier to love if you customize it just a little bit
有几个插件可以让GDB变得更好
there are several plugins that make GDB better
我强烈推荐其中一款
I highly recommend one of these
此时我最熟悉的是pwndbg
I'm most familiar with pwndbg at this point
但是PEDA有它的长处
but PEDA has its adherence and
PWNGDB也有它的长处
pwngdb has its adherence
选择一个并安装它，将使GDB更加简单
pick one and install it to make GDB much much simpler
更容易使用
much easier to use
你甚至可以把它安装在挑战环境的容器里
you can actually even if you want to install it inside that container for the challenge problems
设置好，它就会一直存在
and set it up and then it'll stay around
因为你的主目录是会被持久化的
because your home directory is persistent
真棒，这就是关于shellcode挑战要讲的全部内容
awesome that is all I have for shellcode challenges
祝你好运
good luck on those assignments